My name is Frank Azaya from Endo State. I was one of the deportees from Libya two days ago.
Before I left I was staying in River State. I was doing business there.
I was going to Libya from there to Europe to go and live a better life. As I was going
on the way, the car we take to Libya, some people died in the car.
We think that it is a very easy journey
So on our way going; we were forty in number in the car, some people died.
God helped us. He took us to Libya safely.
Along the line as we were about to cross to Europe; we paid for the connection men to us to Europe.
As were are going we take the ..... in Libya.
On our way going close to international waters. The people they call Osama.
they now come and cut us on top of the sea.
They take us to prison under ground. It's a very hidden place.
Nobody know that that place is existing. A lot of Africans that are there are a lot, up to 500 people.
They use that place to do business; but when they arrest people they go and sell them to people.
People become bad human beings there. We were there almost four months and some weeks.
In our presence; people were dying there. Everyday they give us one havza in the day.
Morning and evening. We were there and we crying to God.
So one day; one Senegalese man now came there.
He brought a phone from outside to a brother there.
Just to be clear brother; this underground prison that you were kept in; noone was
allowed to have a phone or any such device in prison, you were just kept there
in that room unable to go out for more than four months.
So as he bring the phone we now collected the phone.
This is a friend of mine he said," Ok what do we do about the issue now?"
I said ok , let's tell people to come and help us.
out of this place here, because nobody knows about that prison in Libya there.
So as you have heard before, I was talking, calling upon T.B. Joshua
Adiboye people in the world to come and help us; that was July 7. People in the world to come and help us.
So you you recorded this video inside a cell within the the Libyan prison.
Which was underground and you were calling on the Nigerian authorities.
You mentioned the names of several prominent men of God asking for help to release you from this prison.
Yes, I did this just for two days it was over. In the prison there; they received the video.
They now investigate; so I am the one who send the video
So they come to me. They point me that I am the one who did the video.
So they come to me, the man said ok they will hand me to death.
I was thinking that.....
Ok just before going ahead; people of God we can see on the side of the screen.
the video in question. Many people who are familiar with social media may have actually watched this video.
as it was spread around the internet showing the condition of the deportees
in Nigeria. He sent it to a friend telling him that they should expose this to the world
for people to know how they are suffering and what they are facing within the confines of
this underground prison. So you said two days after you send this video;
tell us what happened to you brother.
Though they now did see the video for the prison there. So the owner of the prison;
he now come and investigate concerning the video. People now they now point me that
I am the one who send the video. The man take me out of the prison.
He said he will sentence me to death.
So they take me to the back yard they put chain on my neck, so they hang me.
And before I go to the journey, crossing the water; I dream about this our
father here T.B. Joshua in the dream. I saw him in the dream,
as he was praying for me. So as we were in the prison there, they take me to the back yard.
They go and hang there me with the chain.
In the morning, there were thinking that I'm dead.
They now come, release me. So they take me to go and throw me
inside the forest; getting there they found out that I'm still walking.
So they brought me to back door prison.
Ok so we want to understand very clearly. As a punishment, for recording this video
you were hung with chains over night until they believed you had died.
They now took your body and took you to the forest.
What did they do when they go to the forest? What was their intention?
So what is there, they take shovel to dig the ground so that they can bury me there.
So others tell me that ; they now find that I'm still walking.
You are still breathing. (Yes)
As they carried you, your body was lifeless, you were limp. They thought you had died.
But as they were about to throw you into the shallow grave they discovered that he was still breathing.
Yeah. They now brought me back to prison. As I was there, so they locked me
in a single cell at the underground there.
So two days; and the men now come to me that I must pay 10 000 dinars.
to divide to Nigerian money, 500 000 naira
So I was there oo, after four days. I tell the men that I don't have that kind of money.
My people now, in Nigeria here, they now scaredly run they send me the amount of 180 000 naira
what Libya money is 10 500 dinars. I paid them, this what I have.
He collected the money. He now say keep him here.
So after one week interval, ION now intervened for the issue.
As ION now come to the prison; they now bring the whole Nigerian people out of the prison.
Register their name so that will face deportation.
The men said lock me inside the room. They said they will not deport me.
Why? Because I'm the one who do the video.
So as they register those people, even my people here, they now tell ION that;
somebody inside the room do do the video. They not allow this young man to come out there.
That is how they advanced it for Tripoli.
They now called our Embassy in Tripoli there.
So they now called the ION people to come back to the prison again
to come and register me. And the next day, they now come to the prison.
They tell the owner of the prison that Embassy is not involved for the issue.
That they open the gate so that I will register.
That's how they bring me out of the prison.
So finally they now register me.The first day I found myself in Nigeria.
I am happy to be here. Actually I said let me go to this place to come and share my testimony.
To thank, appreciate the name of God come alive. As I appreciate the name of God
for all what God has been using this T.B. Joshua to do for people.
Before I got there, I saw in the dream the way he was doing both spiritual and physical.
That's why I'm here today to come and appreciate the name of God
appreciating you also, the Lord will bless you in the name of Jesus.
Amen.
Let's just hear a very quick word from the brother beside him who actually took that very video.
Brother if you introduce yourself and tell us that video you took.
My name is Efemena Amu Steven. I am from Delta State,
I am among the Libyan deportees that were brought to Nigeria from Libya on Thursday.
And I'm also among the prisoners that were being locked up in Osama prison in Libya.
The journey to Libya was horrible and the experience, it was like a horror film.
When we were finally caught in the sea; we were taken to the prison.
We got to discover that the prison, is meant for business and not for deportation.
If not for the video that we did; that we sent out, we wouldn't have been here today.
cause that video we expose the activities of the prison and that was out almost the whole of
the other African people, from other countries, that was how they got their freedom.
We thank God that the brothers here are out safely. Let's just hear from the other brother as well.
Please introduce yourself and tell us your own side the story.
Emmanuel! ( God is with us -Matthew 1:23)
My names are Miracle Chidi. I am from Imo State.
My journey to Libya was horrible. I was heading to Europe and not Libya.
But unfortunately I found myself in Libya after spending years.
On that Mediterranean Sea, we spend three days on top of that sea.
Even when we got to International we lost souls there.
Osama; hold us captive there in the sea. We were now taken back to Libya.
We thought he was about to deport us , not knowing that it was for a business.
He took us to the prison. We spend months there. People died.
Beatings everyday, no food. No good water. No treatments. I pass out blood
for weeks in that prison almost pleading every day crying and sharing tears just to get just nothing
Finally some people born there died if it was not for the wisdom that was applied for the video
I don't think if we could have come back to this Nigeria alive because we lost souls every day.
We give glory to God that our brethren are here right now we want to listen to another one
of the deportees who will share a slightly different experience concerning what happened
to him when he underwent this horrific journey into Libya so brother
Please introduce yourself and tell us your own side of this story.
My names are Mr Esosa Odike. I'm from Edo States.
What really happened in my journey? I experienced something that I have never seen in my entire life.
I went to Libya just to cross and we are not there to stay.
but unfortunately the worst part that has seen in that journey was on top of the sea, the Mediterranean Sea.
I spend three days on top of the Mediterranean Sea,
when they push us because they call it lapalapa, the boat they use
its just a polin the one they use for canopy. They sew it together
pump it, fill it with gas and air that is what they put passengers
The lowest passenger they will load on it is 120 , 122, 130 will cross the Mediterranean Sea,that has no end
So we were on top of the Mediterranean Sea...
How many people were in the boat that you were in? How many people?
In my boat we were 122. We spend three days without no rescue, the sea
is three colours, white , blue, black. After moving for three days without
getting rescue, so we have to turn back. The heavy wave came and the boat capsized.
But the greatest thing that I see that gave me joy when we were in our camp;
before they push us, we always pray and I always watch Emmanuel TV
in my GoTV at home. And we always pray with the name of God of Prophet T.B. Joshua.
On top of the sea, I begin to call Prophet T.B. Joshua.
But while 118 people died in my boat, remaining 4.
So among the 4; I was number 1, my brother that put on the black jacket 2
and 2 other girls. We were the only 4 people that survived in that 122.
So, I don't even believe I will survive so when I see myself in Nigeria.
I didn't believe. Even as I am here I didn't even believe I'm still alive
Could you share with us brother, how was it that you were able to survive and what did you see
at that moment that shocked you when you were in the ocean?
After 2 days the third day; we decide to turn back the boat,
the captain say aah we should return the boat because there is no rescue.
As we were coming, so there was a wave, automatically before the wave get to where we are;
I saw people that were dining and wining in the camp
begin to manipulate , begin to change into vipers
they begin to grow teeth. They begin to grow fingers, begin to attack each other.
If anyone bites the other one , the other one will turn to the same thing.
They begin to attack themselves. Then I now see that in the midst of humans there are vipers.
I have never seen it in my life before. But on top of the boat I see people turning to vipers.
Ok, we want to understand very clearly. At the point when the boat was about to capsize:
one of the people inside the boat, you saw them suddenly as in their teeth grew
and they started biting other members within the people on that group on the boat.
And what would happen to the people that they bit?
What happened to the people they bite, assuming if they bite me;
me I will bite another person, that one will bite another person and anybody that they bite
will change, they will be like them. So immediately as the boat break
from the middle; because they put a board on top,
and immediately as the boat break into two; so the lapalapa now cover
so everybody that was sitting on the center about 70 to 77
immediately all of them fell inside the water.
Yes all of them fell inside the water. Some of them came up again, they entered the boat
instantly, men, women boys, girls, pregnant women they begin to manipulate.
Pregnant women that were in that boat were up to about 40. All of them died.
The babies that were up there, so they begin to die. I see vipers, people growing
teeth. They would just bite, as they bite - I am still seeing the picture.
As they bite, the other one will bite the other, the other one will bite the other one
So I begin to be scared, so I will be running back.
calling God of Pastor T.B. Joshua . But when I see the miracle of God in the camp
and in the water especially on the Mediterranean Sea; I believe I will die in the hands of God.
Ok so, our brother is re narrating his experience what he saw with his own eyes
when he was on the top of the ocean as his boat capsized. This is not aaah
a horror film or something that he just imagined. This was his own experience
as people were dying in his midst. Brother how did you actually survive? What did you do?
How did you manage to survive when all the of the 90% of your colleagues drowned?
On top of the boat, after 3 days; after we saw people on top of the sea they look like birds.
Dead bodies the water begin to float them so I keep holding the boat because on that boat
there is a rope that they put round the board so that rope lead to the general valve.
So I hold the rope and we were still calling the God of Pastor T.B. Joshua. I hold the boat
without no shirt. I was with just a knicker. I was not with a life jacket.
I was on top of the boat then after 3 days; the third day, a ship came.
there was.... those Chinese people were inside.
So they took us to the ship. So promised that they will give us shelter they will take us to their place.
But when we were sleeping then we saw some policemen putting on soldier uniform.
So they were Libyans, wake us up and they took me and my friend and the other two girls.
back to Libya. That is how we have been imprisoned till on Thursday morning,
when they brought us out and deported us.
Let's hear from the other gentleman who was also a survivor on this boat.
As we listen we say that there was 120 plus people in the boat and only 4 survived
two of them are in our midst. So brother can you share briefly your own side of this experience.
My names are Iboye Ufuoma. I am from Delta State
The worsest thing I have ever experienced in my life was is encountering on that route to Libya.
I have not seen a thing like this before.
But the most the most worseful one is in the sea
Likewise my brother have said, that was the worsest experience.
We were 122 in the boat. We were seeking asylum abroad,
to make sure we can survive. So we approach, we been in the sea for 3 days.
At the end of the day, a mighty wave come and smash our boat and the boat tear into two.
Out of that boat, inside the boat, everybody in the middle sank inside the water.
So it was remaining only 4 of us, and the 4, 2 were women, the other two were boys.
So I have been in that water; all my leg were eaten up by fish. Fish were eating under my leg.
And do you know my body was...I don't know because the salty water is eating up all my body,
and there were fish feeding under my leg, so a thought came to me because when we were in the camp
we were always using the God of T.B. Joshua to pray.
The mind come to me and said - why don't shout the name of God of T.B. Joshua.
If all those things that is growing up here, because I finally notice that there were people manifesting
a kind of things I have never experienced before. People were growing up teeth.
Everyone that fell inside the water when it comes out, they come out with another shape.
They were growing up teeth, growing up fingers. They were biting the one inside the boat again.
So everywhere was just scattered.
Brother, you know people, it's difficult for people to believe what you are saying
because it's a strange thing. You mean that when people were drowning as they entered the water
that very same person when they came back; you would see their features have changed?
Their teeth had grown, they had grown claws and they became very wild
and aggressive. Is this what you yourself saw with your eyes on this sea?
That was exactly what I experienced. People were growing up teeth.
The people we were meeting with inside the boat were growing up teeth again
to eat up the people inside the boat. That was how the boat finally cap sided.
And it was remaining...after the boat cap sided; it was remaining only 4 of us.
This my brother here; and some other two women.
Those ones have gone to their various places.
So it was terrible, so terrible that I have not seen in my life but I have witnessed it.
But to the Glory of God you survived. You said even your skin changed colour because
of the salt in the water.
My skin totally changed because the water is salt water.
It eats up my body. And the fish were feeding under my legs. So immediately I call on the name of
the God of T.B. Joshua, I ... the next day of it , we saw a ship that come from nowhere
that rescue us. Inside the ship they were white men from Chinese.
And they told us that we shouldn't worry after they finish the rescue they said we shouldn't worry,
that they will give us shelter that will make us ok. That they will handle us to their country.
That they will take us to their country and take good care of us.
In the night when we were sleeping, suddenly we saw some people putting on military uniform.
They came to wake us up. I said aah, to my mind, to my greatest surprise I said - what is this?
You people promised us that , they will take us to their place.So what am I seeing?
They say we should get up in Libya language ; they call it asma tahala tahala.
I said aah, tahala what the shi### is tahala
So what our brother is explaining is that; even after suffering in such a condition
seeing, witnessing his own colleagues drowning before his eyes, some of them even transforming
into demonic figures as a result of that death
even after that way he survived, he was still taken back to Lybia into captivity.
So the effort all the years and months he spent going abroad in attempt to reach Europe;
he never even reached the destination he tried to get to.
He went back to Lybia , and back to the prison.
And that was how you finally were deported back to Nigeria with your colleagues two days ago.
Is that right?
Yes, yes that was how I finally deported here to Nigeria and I had spend a lot of months in the prisons.
Eating abza daily.
Let's just hear from the other young man there to quickly conclude the experiences
of our brothers. Brother just introduce yourself to us and tell us what happened to you when you were in Libya.
My name is Mathias Edegbe. I am from Eboni States Abakaliki Town.
I went to Libya last year April. As I went to Lybia. I went to cross to Europe.
We reach on top of Mediterranean Sea. They arrest us, they take u back to dry land.
As we were coming back to dry land, the boat capsized.
People died. So they called rescued. Some people they were rescued did go back to dry land.
So I was trying to escape from them. The street boys they catch me and put back
to the prison. As I am trying to pray that day; that was around 12 o'clock in the night.
The Arab man came, he said "What is happening, why are we making noise inside the prison?"
I told him that I want to pray. That is how he bring gun and start to shoot inside the house.
Some many people died.He hold me and used bottle and knife
and cut my hand. Look at my hand. Almost my teeth come out of my mouth.
They use gun and break my head. I received some injury inside my body
as we are talking just now. So that one passed.
This year; I still tried to cross to Europe.
So brother the scars we are seeing on your arms are wounds that were inflicted
upon you in the Libyan prison when they told you to stop making noise
during your prayer. They used a glass to open or tear skin in your arm
and even removed displaced the bone in your arm. Is that right?
So what we are seeing is the bone coming out sir?
This is the bone. They beat me and used knife, the bottle and cut my hand.
So this year, I went to cross again. Almost the same thing that happened last year that's how it happened.
And that is how you were deported back to Nigeria with your colleagues. (Yes)
Ok let's finally hear from the lady at the far end who actually came with a very small child .
Libya Deportees Share Life Experiences.
Can you introduce yourself to us and tell us your own experiences in Libya.
My name is Ada I stay in Nigeria before when one of my friends from Germany
said I should come. So I reached Saba. There the guy came to pick me up.
So I went to see the connection man to help me find work.
When I got there, I did work for two months.
The woman came, she beat me. As she beat me she said why did I bring the cup
and I bring a plate I don't know what is a cup in arabic.
So she beat me. There they are used to stay on clean ground not mopping.
They use something else.
So as I clean and finish no food.
Instead of telling me to and remove the tea cup
She begin beating me again
I say I better run away from the big person like that
Ok so for the benefit of those who may not understand what our sister is explaining.
She is speaking in pidgin English, She is explaining how is among the people that
traveled illegally through the deserts to Libya
and upon arriving she was actually sold into slavery, where she was forced
to work under a particular lady who maltreated her, beats her mercilessly.
Even she was so confused as a result of the beating that if she was asked to bring
something she would bring the wrong thing which could lead to a lot of beating
and torture and she asked herself, is this what she traveled to Nigeria for,
to work as a slave. So can you tell us sister, how did you now end up in prison?
And what led to you being here with this little baby?
As I go around on the road, I meet one boy on the road.
I ask him , I say I need help. He can't help me . I said help me, put me in a house.
From there he now give me belle. He can't still help me.
She's explaining that she ran away from this particular lady and on the street
She met some man who promised to help her the man took her to his house and that man
impregnated her, So tell us what happened after that after he became pregnant for this man.
We can't go for pushing they can't push us go sea side, that is where we
went go cross Europe. And I kept belle. Each time, there on top of the sea now
Call the child, call the child so from there we could see a plane
A plane follow up. We don't know the plane where they direct us now, Italian plane.
An Arab man they drive the boat. So we can't go the wrong side.
But here now water got spoil. People even say last prayer. They don't even pray finish.
Who stayed at this edge, and who stayed at this edge, as the water they slap.
People they fall enter inside. Now I see myself I die for this sea.
So they try , they try God try going bring one rescue, Libya rescue.
So they rescue us. As they rescue us we get the for prison for like 2 months.
I get confused.
Okay, so just to explain what our sister is saying with this man that impregnated her;
they attempted to travel on the sea to Europe through entering the rubber dinghy
known as lapalapa - a very small boat, inflatable boat.
As they were going across the Mediterranean Ocean while she was pregnant.
Although they saw a plane above which they believed was a signal that they would be rescued .
At that point, storm set in and people at the extreme end of the bout , began to fall into the water.
They died by drowning and then finally a boat came to rescue them
but they discovered that it was a Libyan boat who took them back to Libya,
and took them to prison. So whilst there in prison, tell us what happened there.
So we get there the prison they come bust us, now they run.
As the guy who gave me the belle; before he run, he say he going to give me number,
when I go tell locate him people. He not can give me, I not see him that night when they all move.
Before I know now , the car run. Now on one them come meet me say aah that boy run
leave you here what can do now. I say I am not aware where to start from
and he never give me collect the number. So I no go hear from them for almost
2 months now, I no go hear from them again.
So I don't even know..in fact I no even know... where to even locate them.
Our sister is explaining that; whilst they were in prison, the owner of the pregnancy,
her boyfriend burst out of the prison escaped with several others inmates.
That she told, he told her to follow, but because she was heavily pregnant
she could not. And even before he left, he had not given her contact details of his family.
So there was no trace of him. She doesn't know now whether he's alive or dead
She doesn't know the number or name of any of his family members and to this point
since he ran away from the prison, she has no idea of his whereabouts
Mrs Ada & Baby. Libya Deportee Life Experience
So we are seeing our sister overcome by emotion we can imagine what it means
for the father of her child to have disappeared and she has no ways of tracing or knowing the family
or even whether he's alive or dead right now
And we can understand what our sister is passing through the reason why she is crying.
Tell us the baby you are holding.
So inside the prison, nobody to help. I got to call one Yoruba girl whether they call me
When she can't help me, now she get to use granite soil to rub my vagina, to rub my back
The baby head now don't come outside. I do push , push, push for inside the prison there.
So as God may have it; That's how I take the baby , the piki.
No treatment , nothing , nothing. Even my belle be still big because
I don't know I can not feel come out the blood from inside so it did not come outside.
So now I a come here so
Okay, people of God, we are listening to our sister. A question sister.
How old is this baby right now you are holding?
A week and three days
So we're hearing from our sister the baby is just one week and three days old
She delivered the baby in the Libyan prison
on ..without any medical assistance with just the prisoners who were around
her to help her push one week after that, she was among those who are deported to Nigeria
she has no way of knowing where the father of this child is or contacting his family
and that's why she's among those that came to the Synagogue Church Of All Nations
to seek supports and help. Now people of God, we know that are The Synagogue Church of All Nations
We have been regularly taking care of those who are deported from Libya
Nigerians deported from Libya. Individuals who are before us are among the people
who arrived nearly 100 they arrived from Libya and they came
Directly to the SCOAN to seek supports
So once again Prophet TB Joshua supported that group with 2.4 million naira
to help them go back to their various states take care of them given food and
enable them to start their lives back in Nigeria with something
as a result of their terrible traumatic experiences abroad.
This is not the first time; regular viewers of Emmanuel TV will know that Prophet T.B. Joshua
has eh with the support of Emmanuel TV Partners has been regularly
taking care of Nigerians deported from Libya and this set is just one of many
who have visited the SCOAN. Right now for the people who are here in our midst
Prophet T.B. Joshua said for the seven who are here right now;
We are here to present to you right now the sum of 1 million naira
This is the sum of 1 million naira for the seven who are here in our midst,
to support each and every single one of you to start a new life in Christ Jesus.
To care for our mother here with a little child. When with making God's word the standard for your lives.
So once again this is 1 million naira for the seven deportees who are here
to enable them to start their lives afresh in Christ Jesus.
Let's put our hands together for Jesus Christ
Libya Deportees Receive 1 Million Naira From Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV Partners
Thank God for what God has done for us today -mother help me thank God.
On behalf of Prophet TB Joshua and the Emmanuel TV partners
this group of Libya deportees will receive over 1 million naira to support them and
for their new life in Christ Jesus, so each and every one of the men will receive
one hundred and fifty thousand naira each and the mother with her child
will receive 200 hundred thousand naira.
My name is Mr. Osousa Odgeye. I so much appreciate what the man of God have done in my life
Because all the years and the debt I have passed through in the land of Libya.
Within the twinkle of an eye; he wiped every where he give my life a meaning.
I was give 150,000 naira to start a new life
May God continually to bless him for his wonderful work in my life.
My name is Frank Azeya from Edo States, Deportee from Lybia
I came with empty hand. I cried to T.B. Joshua and he wiped away my tears.
With my colleagues, we came him, he give us an amount of 1,30 million naira.
Each each person receive amount of 150 thousand naira to start a new life.
We don't know how to thank you. We thank the Lord will reward you.
The Lord will bless you. I and my colleagues here; we so much appreciate you.
Thank you very much Sir
Libya Deportees Receive 1 Million Naira From Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV Partners
TT Monica Asefa 29/10/18